// Questions array
const questions = [
       {
        "numb": 151,
        "question": "What is the timing of late secondary bleeding?",
        "answer": "later than 7 days",
        "options": [
            "1-3 days",
            "no earlier than 14 days",
            "3-5 days",
            "5-7 days",
            "later than 7 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 152,
        "question": "What kind of bleeding causes blood to be excreted with vomit?",
        "answer": "gastric",
        "options": [
            "arterial",
            "venous",
            "urinary",
            "gastric",
            "pulmonary"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 153,
        "question": "What is the purpose of the first aid for bleeding at the accident?",
        "answer": "temporary blood stop",
        "options": [
            "psychological support of the victim",
            "temporary blood stop",
            "surgery",
            "ambulance call",
            "anesthesia"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 154,
        "question": "The maximum duration of applying the tourniquet is:",
        "answer": "90 min",
        "options": [
            "30 min",
            "60 min",
            "120 min",
            "180 min",
            "90 min"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 155,
        "question": "The physical methods of stopping bleeding include:",
        "answer": "cryodestruction",
        "options": [
            "vessel bypass",
            "cryodestruction",
            "laser irradiation of blood",
            "vessel ligation throughout",
            "ultrasound scanning of the spleen"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 156,
        "question": "Thrombin as a mean to stop bleeding is used:",
        "answer": "locally",
        "options": [
            "for embolization of vessel",
            "intraarterially",
            "locally",
            "intravenously",
            "intraperitoneally"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 157,
        "question": "The donors of reserve are donors who:",
        "answer": "donate blood when there is a need for an institution",
        "options": [
            "systematically involved in donation for several years",
            "have a rare blood type",
            "immunized with a certain antigen donors",
            "donate blood regularly",
            "donate blood when there is a need for an institution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 158,
        "question": "The storage period of blood when using glugicir is:",
        "answer": "21 days",
        "options": [
            "35 days",
            "3 days",
            "5 days",
            "8-10 days",
            "21 days"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 159,
        "question": "Antishock drugs include:",
        "answer": "Ringer's solution",
        "options": [
            "hemodesis",
            "polyglucin",
            "casein hydrolysate",
            "polyamine",
            "Ringer's solution"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 160,
        "question": "Detoxification drugs include:",
        "answer": "polydez",
        "options": [
            "aminosol",
            "Ringer's solution",
            "voluven",
            "polyglucin",
            "polydez"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 161,
        "question": "What is ablood type?",
        "answer": "a set of erythrocyte antigens",
        "options": [
            "a set of immune antibodies",
            "whey proteins",
            "a set of acquired antibodies",
            "a set of erythrocyte antigens",
            "a set of leukocyte antigens"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 162,
        "question": "What is the significance of antigens and antibodies of the ABO system in blood transfusion practice?",
        "answer": "determine the compatibility of transfused blood",
        "options": [
            "characterize the state of the body",
            "they are not of fundamental importance",
            "allow you to determine the required volume of blood transfusion",
            "determine the compatibility of transfused blood",
            "all of the above is true"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 163,
        "question": "On the first day after a properly performed hemotransfusion, the following complication occurs more often:",
        "answer": "pyrogenic reactions",
        "options": [
            "acute renal failure",
            "thromboembolism",
            "acute dilation of the heart",
            "pyrogenic reactions",
            "acute cerebrovascular"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 164,
        "question": "The blood type during the transfusion:",
        "answer": "checked before each blood transfusion",
        "options": [
            "checked before the first blood transfusion",
            "it is not checked, there is enough data in the passport",
            "it is not checked, there is enough anamnesis data",
            "it is not checked, there is enough data in the medical history",
            "checked before each blood transfusion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 165,
        "question": "Hemotransfusion and obstetric anamnesis before the blood transfusion can:",
        "answer": "prevent possible hemotransfusion complications",
        "options": [
            "prevent possible hemotransfusion complications",
            "identify hereditary diseases",
            "determine the Rh affiliation and blood type of the patient",
            "urgently pick up onated blood",
            "make a medical history"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 166,
        "question": "How long can blood taken to determine the Rh factor be stored at a temperature of +4, +8C?",
        "answer": "2-3 days",
        "options": [
            "5-6 days",
            "10-12 hours",
            "2-3 hours",
            "2-3 days",
            "up to 1 day"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 167,
        "question": "How long after hemotransfusion is it necessary to carry out dynamic monitoring of the patient?",
        "answer": "3 hours",
        "options": [
            "1 hour",
            "3 hours",
            "the patient does not need to be monitored",
            "4 hrs",
            "2hrs"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 168,
        "question": "What complications can occur on the first day after technically correct hemotransfusion?",
        "answer": "pyrogenic reactions",
        "options": [
            "thromboembolism",
            "acute renal failure",
            "acute enlargement of the heart",
            "acute cerebrovascular accident",
            "pyrogenic reactions"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 169,
        "question": "What concentration is medical gelatin administered intravenously?",
        "answer": "10%",
        "options": [
            "50%",
            "10%",
            "20%",
            "30%",
            "40%"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 170,
        "question": "At what concentration is thrombin administered intravenously?",
        "answer": "intravenously is not administered",
        "options": [
            "0.25%",
            "1%",
            "10%",
            "intravenously is not administered",
            "5%"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 171,
        "question": "Which drug (anticoagulant) binds calcium ions and forms difficult to dissociate salts?",
        "answer": "sodium citrate",
        "options": [
            "vitamin K",
            "sodium citrate",
            "phenylin",
            "sinkumar",
            "calcium chloride"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 172,
        "question": "How long does heaprin take effect after injection?",
        "answer": "immediately after injection",
        "options": [
            "after 5-6 hours",
            "after 1-2 hours",
            "immediately after injection",
            "after 3-4 hours",
            "after 8 hours"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 173,
        "question": "After what time does dicumarin begin to act after injection?",
        "answer": "after 3-5 days",
        "options": [
            "after 3-4 hours",
            "after 3-5 days",
            "after 8 hours",
            "after 1-2 days",
            "after 5-6 hours"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 174,
        "question": "What is the duration of action of heparin?",
        "answer": "2-6 hours",
        "options": [
            "10-24 hours",
            "2-6 hours",
            "2-3 days",
            "7-10 hours",
            "10-15 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 175,
        "question": "Blood in (III) groups can be injected to individuals:",
        "answer": "with blood groups II and III",
        "options": [
            "with blood groups II and III",
            "only with blood type III",
            "only with blood groups III and IV",
            "with any blood type",
            "only with blood type II"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 176,
        "question": "The group of hemodynamic blood substitutes includes:",
        "answer": "polydesis",
        "options": [
            "albumin",
            "polydesis",
            "globulin",
            "polyglucine",
            "protein"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 177,
        "question": "To conduct a biological test, enter:",
        "answer": "three times 25 ml of blood",
        "options": [
            "two times 10 ml of blood with an interval of 3 minutes, watching the patient",
            "three times 25 ml of blood",
            "25 ml of blood once and monitor the patient's condition for 5 minutes",
            "three times 10 ml of blood with an interval of 3 minutes, watching the patient",
            "25 ml of blood, monitor the patient's condition for 5 minutes"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 178,
        "question": "After the blood transfusion, the nurse monitors:",
        "answer": "pulse, blood pressure, diuresis and temperature",
        "options": [
            "pulse, blood pressure, diuresis and temperature",
            "pulse and temperature",
            "arterial blood pressure",
            "pulse and blood pressure",
            "diuresis and temperature"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 179,
        "question": "The blood component with the most pronounced hemostatic effect is:",
        "answer": "erythrocyte suspension",
        "options": [
            "erythrocyte suspension",
            "erythrocyte mass",
            "leukocyte mass",
            "platelet mass",
            "plasma"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 180,
        "question": "Donated blood is stored in the refrigerator at a temperature of:",
        "answer": "4-6C",
        "options": [
            "4-6C",
            "7-10C",
            "(-5C)",
            "(-2C)",
            "0-2C"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 181,
        "question": "Special operations include:",
        "answer": "endoscopic",
        "options": [
            "radical",
            "neurosurgical",
            "endoscopic",
            "simultaneous",
            "diagnostic "
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 182,
        "question": "A surgical operation is called:",
        "answer": "mechanical effects on organs and tissues performed for the purpose of treatment and diagnosis",
        "options": [
            "mechanical effects on organs and tissues performed for the purpose of treatment and diagnosis",
            "operations performed using endoscopic devices",
            "treatment of the patient by detecting a pathological lesion and removing it",
            "separation of the integumentary tissues to remove the pathological focus",
            "a set of measures providing for prompt access and prompt reception"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 183,
        "question": "Emergency surgery is not performed:",
        "answer": "in case of malignant tumors",
        "options": [
            "with arterial bleeding",
            "in case of malignant tumors",
            "with compression of the brain",
            "with peritonitis",
            "with a strained pneumothorax"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 184,
        "question": "One of the stages of the preoperative period is:",
        "answer": "diagnostic stage",
        "options": [
            "preventive stage",
            "preclinical stage",
            "rehabilitation stage",
            "diagnostic stage",
            "treatment stage"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 185,
        "question": "Diseases requiring emergency surgery are:",
        "answer": "pinched inguinal hernia, perforated stomach ulcer",
        "options": [
            "stomach cancer, shoulder lipoma",
            "malignant brain tumor",
            "hydrothorax",
            "pinched inguinal hernia, perforated stomach ulcer",
            "furuncle"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 186,
        "question": "Manipulation that can be attributed to therapeutic operations:",
        "answer": "correction of shoulder dislocation",
        "options": [
            "correction of shoulder dislocation",
            "trial laparotomy",
            "gastroscopy",
            "finger examination of the rectum",
            "laryngoscopy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 187,
        "question": "Manipulation that can be attributed to diagnostic operations:",
        "answer": "trial laparotomy",
        "options": [
            "trial laparotomy",
            "correction of shoulder dislocation",
            "appendectomy",
            "finger examination of the rectum",
            "laryngoscopy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 188,
        "question": "Surgery for vital signs is performed with:",
        "answer": "ongoing bleeding",
        "options": [
            "varicose veins of the lower extremities",
            "obliterating endarteritis",
            "a benign tumor",
            "malignant tumor",
            "ongoing bleeding"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 189,
        "question": "Preoperative measures that reduce the risk of infection of the surgical wound are:",
        "answer": "all of the above",
        "options": [
            "cleansing of the gastrointestinal tract",
            "bath",
            "antibiotic therapy",
            "all of the above",
            "shaving the skin"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 190,
        "question": "Specify an event aimed at PREVENTING pulmonary complications after surgery:",
        "answer": "breathing exercises",
        "options": [
            "gastric lavage",
            "breathing exercises",
            "cold on the stomach",
            "administration of iron preparations",
            "inhalation of nitrous oxide"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 191,
        "question": "Information about previous illnesses and injuries is described in the medical history section:",
        "answer": "life history",
        "options": [
            "life history",
            "additional examination",
            "complaints",
            "history of the disease development",
            "examination of the place of the disease"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 192,
        "question": "Information about heredity should be reflected in the medical history section:",
        "answer": "life history",
        "options": [
            "history of the development of the present disease",
            "life history",
            "local status",
            "complaints",
            "results of additional examination"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 193,
        "question": "Physical examination methods do not include:",
        "answer": "endoscopy",
        "options": [
            "auscultation",
            "percussion",
            "palpation",
            "auscultoafriction",
            "endoscopy"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 194,
        "question": "Additional examination methods include:",
        "answer": "CT scan",
        "options": [
            "palpation",
            "determination of the apical shock",
            "percussion",
            "CT scan",
            "auscultation"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 195,
        "question": "An invasive examination method implies:",
        "answer": "a method in which the integrity of the integumentary tissues is violated and, accordingly, there is a possibility of complications in the form of bleeding, surgical infection, damage to internal organs",
        "options": [
            "a method in which the integrity of the integumentary tissues is violated and, accordingly, there is a possibility of complications in the form of bleeding, surgical infection, damage to internal organs",
            "a method that is safe for the patient",
            "the method associated with the risk of the doctor receiving any harm as a result of contact with the patient",
            "the method associated with the risk of infection of the doctor as a result of his contact with the patient",
            "a method that is safe for both the patient and the doctor"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 196,
        "question": "The main difference between a surgical medical history and therapeutic in:",
        "answer": "the presence of the section \"local status\"",
        "options": [
            "setting the time of the onset of the disease to the minute",
            "a shorter and more specific statement of complaints",
            "a more detailed description of the musculoskeletal system",
            "mandatory entry into the medical history of information about previously performed surgical interventions to the patient",
            "the presence of the section \"local status\""
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 197,
        "question": "The sequence of examination of the patient os as follows:",
        "answer": "examination, palpation, percussion, auscultation",
        "options": [
            "",
            "examination, percussion, palpation, auscultation",
            "palpation, examination, percussion, auscultation",
            "examination, palpation, percussion, auscultation",
            "auscultation, percussion, palpation, examination"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 198,
        "question": "Indications for surgery should be described in the section medical history:",
        "answer": "peroperative epicrisis",
        "options": [
            "local objective examination",
            "protocol of surgery",
            "peroperative epicrisis",
            "general objective examination",
            "complaints"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 199,
        "question": "List the information to describe the operation in the medical history:",
        "answer": "description of the pathological changes detected during the operation, description of the course of the operation, its completion",
        "options": [
            "information about the amount of suture and other consumables used",
            "the degree of participation of each surgeon in the operation",
            "access used, cut length",
            "description of the removed macropreparation",
            "description of the pathological changes detected during the operation, description of the course of the operation, its completion"
        ]
    },
    {
        "numb": 200,
        "question": "Preparation of the intestine in the preoperative period provides for the appointment of:",
        "answer": "cleansing enemas",
        "options": [
            "probe power supply",
            "a slag-free diet",
            "cleansing enemas",
            "cold on the stomach",
            "expectorant drugs"
        ]
    }
];
